a lot of people have a sense that a felt
sense that things are starting to break
down do you sympathize with that and how
would you sort of sum up what that means
if we look at the history of the thing
we call civilization to date one very
obvious thing that we notice is that all
the early civilizations don't still
exist whether we look at the Mayas the
Aztecs the Egyptians the Roman Empire
the Greek Empire the they all collapsed
and so the precedent is actually that
civilization collapses not that it
maintains the real difference is that
this is the first time we have a
completely global civilization there
really is no such thing as USA or China
separate from each other when you
understand globalized materials
economies technology economics where
there's actually no country in the world
that can make its own consumer
electronics right without the mining and
manufacturing and you know technology
that happens from around the world so
our process of civilization is one that
has inherently self terminating dynamics
built into it when that happens at a
fully global scale it is a basically the
catastrophe is just unbounded where it
has always been bounded as big as the
Roman Empire was when it fell it wasn't
everything and limited by not only its
total geographical size but the level of
Technology it had it caused
desertification throughout the noble
agriculture but it wasn't able to
destabilize the biosphere writ large in
a hundred years of industrialized
fishing we've removed most of the large
fish species from a water planet right
at 3/4 water planet took three and a
half billion years to get those fish
species and so you recognize that we're
operating the same way that has always
led to war and environmental destruction
and collapse of civilization just
factoring exponential technology and so
when you start to think about
exponential rivalry rivalry dynamics
that lead to polarization that ends up
leading to war but now exponential
warfare it becomes larger than a finite
biosphere can handle and it becomes
existential when you think about
exponential extraction the next one
pollution which means depletion and
accumulation from open loops in a
network diagram you go to an eco system
there are no open loops every thing is
the food for something else there is no
unknowable resource no waste our
civilization is characterized by
materials economy that's linear not
circular so toxicity is depletion on one
side accumulation on the other whether
we're talking about on the depletion
side whether we're talking about species
extinction or biodiversity loss or any
of the issues that we look at there and
on the accumulation side whether we're
talking about co2 levels in the air or
in the water or nitrogen runoff or
degraded uranium or whatever else it is
those are all specific instantiations of
open loops in the way we do civilization
in relationship to the closed loop
dynamics of the ecosystem that both have
a civilization that is increasingly
fragile and that is making increasingly
fragile underlying ecosystem is
basically debasing the substrate upon
which it depends and so when you think
about exponential extraction exponential
pollution that obviously gets larger
than the playing field can handle when
you try and think about exponential
expansion of the monetary supply that
has to be based in goods and services
that can't keep happening when you think
about we compete using narrative and
information when you start to think
about exponential information tech used
for disinformation and for population
control you get to a place where the
information ecology is so broken that
what's actually happening with North
Korea or not are we going to have
nuclear war what's actually happening
with Syria what's actually happening
with Putin's relationship to the Trump
administration how long do we really
have before all the coral die-off like
all the most important questions as to
whether we make it or not as a species
nobody really knows how to make sense of
and so when you have a situation where
you've actually got an exponentially
decreasing sense-making capacity right
an information ecology that is
increasingly more broken with an
exponentially increasing capacity to
make big choices right technology is
basically a lever of our choice making
so a fist has one level of harm and I
extend that to a stone tool it's a
bigger harm to a bronze tool to a gun at
the level of an ICBM that's just a
really big extension of that type
choice-making capacity but when I have
exponentially increased choice-making
capacity with exponentially worse sense
making that always runs into a cliff and
so the underlying dynamics that are
leading to the self-determination that
people feel and sense right now are not
different in kind than the ones that
we've been facing since the beginning of
what we call civilization they're
different in magnitude and in the speed
of process factoring the exponential
curves involved and what is it because
some people talk about the shift being
we can talk about intermit irreal terms
or we can talk about it in terms of an
evolution in consciousness or the way
that we operate what do you sense is
that leap that we need to make in terms
of how we operate you actually have to
think about it on all of those levels to
be able to make sense of it in a
meaningful way otherwise it's kind of
like asking when we are talking about
the health of a person whether that
means the health of their liver or their
kidneys or their blood it's like that
doesn't even make sense you can't
separate those things from each other so
when I think about what economics is
economics is our value system codified
as value equations that determines how
much we value one thing relative to
another thing that determines what we're
incentivized to do and what we confer
power to so if a dead whale is worth a
million dollars on a fishing boat and a
live whale in the ocean is worth nothing
that's a value system codified in a
value equation that then incentivizes
behavior but it also incentivizes
psychopathology right psychopathy
actually I have to shut empathy down
because leaving the whale in the ocean
it I hope she isn't even gonna stay in
the ocean another guy's gonna hunt it
out right so I've got a tragedy of the
Commons so I have to kind of deaden to
be able to do the thing that is
incentivized by the system or somebody
else does and I'm just not effective in
the system so you can't think about the
evolution of human consciousness and the
evolution of economics differently but
if you look at the way economics then
needs to protect its own profit stream
in the way it will learn how to
influence media to control people's
sense making frameworks in the way it
will influence governance again this is
getting to consciousness or the way it
will influence legislation on the nature
of what happens in education to prepare
people for the work force and so the
paradigm shift is basically
everything we need new systems of
governance if we just I mean we think
about how much we love the word
democracy and we love the word democracy
because it's better than tyranny and
it's better than the other like really
horrible systems that we've experienced
at any scale but when Winston Churchill
said democracy is the single worst form
of governance ever created save for all
the other forms what he was saying that
was really insightful was that getting
lots of humans to agree on anything is
just a hard thing to do and we suck at
it and we've never actually done a good
job at it and this is a really flawed
system now we like it because like we
said it's overcoming things that were
even more problematic if you think about
democracy for a moment and whether we're
talking representative democracy or
liquid democracy using a voting currency
or binary vote fundamentally of a
process of saying okay we can't get
everybody to agree beyond a very small
number of people Dunbar number tribe you
can get everybody degree because they
can all be in a conversation together
beyond the level of which you can have a
conversation together you can have a few
people control everything and they can
be in a conversation together some type
of oligarchy or meritocracy but then
you're like no we want most of the
people to agree at least right that
seems like a good idea but somebody puts
forward a proposition to do something
that they think is important based on
their limited sense making that is never
everything that proposition because it
wasn't informed by comprehensive sense
making will always in the process of
benefiting something also damage
something else and so some people love
it based on if what it's benefiting is
directly relevant to them and other
people hate it based on if what it's
damaging is relevant to them you just
created inexorable polarization because
you made shitty propositions and then
ask people to vote yes or no by an Arri
on a shitty proposition so you notice
people actually don't all get to
contribute to the sense making of what a
good proposition would be there's no
kind of collective input there there
isn't even a generation of what would
good mean here and they so really even
their choice making is just yes or no on
a frame that was already controlled and
typically who's going to be able to even
put forward a proposition as someone who
has vested interests and so you're stuck
with polarization in that particular
system right
so we need new systems of governance
that are not any system of governance
the world has ever done so far there are
systems of how do we individually and
collectively make sense of what's going
on make sense of what we actually value
and how those values can be
synergistically satisfied rather than an
a theory of trade-offs with each other
progressively better and how do we
create design that are optimal
synergistic satisfiers so that's totally
new thing governance wise we need
totally new systems of economics we need
totally new systems of Education
healthcare all the way down to at an
individual level a new basis for
identity values our own individual sense
making choice making as long as I think
that I'm an individual that is
fundamentally separate from you and the
biosphere and everything else I can
think about optimizing my own quality of
life independent of and maybe even at
the expense of your quality of life for
the biosphere or anything else as soon
as I get that I start to say okay well
I'm not that tree but what would I be
without trees why would not exist right
well there would be no atmosphere if
they weren't plants photosynthesizing so
I fundamentally am not even a meaningful
concept without plants so if I think of
myself as me that is not fundamentally
interdependent with plants I'm actually
just not even thinking clearly right
it's just a bad ontology it's a bad
semiotic s-- and then I start to run
that and say well what about soil
microbiota and what about and it turns
out that my life depends on the whole
thing right so I am really I can be
better thought of as an emergent
property of this whole thing right not
just a biosphere because what would it
be without the Sun and so as long as I
have a sense of AI that is separate and
maybe even rival ris'n rival risk
competition for some scarce status
resource attention partner or whatever
it is then we have a fundamental basis
for war and in a world of exponentially
increasing technology which means that
the warfare gets to be more and more
consequential that will self terminate
so rival risk dynamics multiplied by
exponential tech self-terminate
exponential tech is inexorable we cannot
put it away so we either figure out anti
rivalry or
we go exceed you an experiment comes to
a completion that's like that's the core
thing figuring out anti rivalry is a
psycho-spiritual process inside of
ourselves can we actually even get along
with our family members can we pay
attention to our emotions and triggers
that hijack us from sovereignty because
the moment I'm getting pissed in my
value system is not to be an angry
person I'm actually hijacked right can I
pay attention to that and actually have
some sovereignty over my own inner state
and how I show up in the world and can
we figure out how to do that
collectively as well but that was my
question how do we give people a sense
of that connection beyond themselves to
give them a felt sense of their
connection to that to the natural world
and to what they depend on so an
important thing to understand about Homo
sapiens that is different than all the
other species as far as we know is you
look at a horse and it's up and walking
in 20 minutes and it takes a human a
year to walk and you think about how we
can be helpless for that long
evolutionarily right like think about
how many 20 minute segments go into a
year to think about how many multiples
of helplessness that is and even a
gorilla or a chimpanzee can hold on to
its mom's fur in the first few minutes
and we can't move our head for three
months we're like okay we are born super
in the autumn this or fetal for a very
long time
and the reason is because all the other
animals evolved to fit an environmental
niche we are niche creators who went to
the Arctic who went out to the islands
who went to the desert who we were able
to create niche adaptation everywhere
and then we made new niches like cities
right and so we couldn't come with a
hardwired program for how to be adaptive
to a certain environment we had to come
not hardwired learn what the environment
was because it used to be super valuable
to throw Spears now we don't throw
Spears that mantri text into other
things so we have to actually be able to
soft wire that means that we are
radically more affected by our
environment than all the other creatures
are - and not just in childhood but even
into adulthood and with neuroplasticity
we are continuously being affected by
our environment so when
you think about that our whole
evolutionary history was in ecosystems
that we depended upon where we were
being well the complexity of nature the
self-organizing dynamics of nature was
what our nervous system was taking in
and getting an intuition for and then we
grow up not connected to any complex
system nature to a little bit of
manicured nature that's about it and all
man-made structures that are complicated
not complex they're all fragile you
bring this house down
it doesn't repair itself you burn a
forest down it does you damage this
camera it doesn't repair itself you cut
me I'll repair myself so we don't even
have an intuition for what nature is or
what complexity is or what
self-organization is because we haven't
spending time around it and we are that
conditioned by what we're around now
younger generations are growing up with
almost their entire life from their
earliest neuroplasticity is
two-dimensional right and that it
responds to them in a way that doesn't
have physics it has some other
pre-programmed in physics so there isn't
even an intuition for how physics works
so all of that is a preface to say
reconditioning a felt sense of our
connectedness with everything is not
actually a trivial thing to do it's a
it's a deep process and there's a
cognitive development that people can
start with which actually matters which
is as soon as you just really think
about it and think about who am i
without plants and Who am I without
pollinators and you realize I don't
exist and you start to get that the that
there is this kind of narcissism that
we're stuck in almost all the time
thinking about me I and it's not even
it's not even a good thought it's like
it's not even a rational way to optimize
my own life let alone the fact that it
creates depression just thinking
cognitively about the interconnectivity
of everything actually helps a lot how
to get a more embodied sense
go spend time in nature do psychedelics
do any kind of state practice that
creates expanded States see how you can
have more intimate relationships with
more people all those things and when
you sketch it out like that it seems
immense the challenge are you are you
hopeful or are you pessimistic I think
that the shift that we are on the
precipice of is not like the shift from
the Dark Ages to the Enlightenment or
even the Agricultural Revolution it's
like more like a shift from single cell
to multicellular life it's like a really
deep fundamental shift in the level and
type of complexity in the nature of
reality that we're talking about
evolution brought about rival risk
dynamics but then it also brought about
our prefrontal cortices our capacity for
abstraction and our ability to do design
and technology Lions can't make
themselves radically more capable as a
predator in a very short period of time
faster than the gazelles can get away
right if they could they could eat all
the gazelles and then go extinct because
they debase the substrate upon which
they lived and so as the great whites
getting a little bit faster the seals
are also getting faster right the whole
system is Co evolving so there are no
radical power asymmetries we start
modeling ourself as an apex predator but
then developing tools that increased our
ability to do that on an exponential
curve when the environment wasn't
increasing its capacity to deal with
that on an exponential curve that self
terminates so that's evolution modified
by technology we need something that is
neither of those things to be able to
take the next step and you know one way
of talking about it is evolution is an
unconscious process rights an
algorithmic process of which species
survive and reproduce and it's extremely
slow and most things fail what makes it
through though has a profound degree of
complexity
design is a much faster process but we
always build things that optimize for
some number of functions that we
intended to talk to minus four but they
affect more things than we intended to
optimize which usually is an externality
there's some you know harm or wasn't
intended evolution by design is
something that is different than just
technology design where we're designing
complicated systems and it's different
than complex design that is unconscious
there's a process by which we can think
of it mythopoetic terms and say the
evolutionary process kept increasing
orderly complexity until we got to the
capacity for abstraction that could
contemplate evolution itself and look at
the principles of evolution see what
it's doing and choose to consciously
participate within mediate evolution
itself and so then we get to move from
we have the possibility of moving from
being parts of the whole that are
competing with each other but moving to
having power that makes that no longer
possible to actually being agents for
the whole because we can't model
ourselves as apex predators when we have
the ability to extinct whole species
rule and whole biospheres make new
species like that's no longer an
adequate model the only thing in nature
that has the kind of ubiquitous power
that can make species and destroy
species and change the geography is
nature itself but now consciously
mediated through agents that have kind
of woken up as that so I think this I
think this next shift is us realizing
that as technology it results from the
our abstraction but focused on parts and
not focused on how the whole thing fits
together as technology is kind of giving
us the power of gods we have to get the
love and wisdom and understanding of
gods or we self-terminate with that
power that's a big task I don't think
that we can say that anything smaller
than that could possibly be adequate you
didn't say whether you think we were
likely to make it on up I think that if
you were to let's take the standard
narrative on evolutionary history and we
say okay there is no life in universe
till
started on earth three billion years ago
so you've got billions of years right
ten plus billion years where there's no
life and a lot of shit happened right
there was a lot of physics and chemistry
and cosmology happening you could say
based on that it's probably that there's
never gonna be this thing called life
because forecasting from the current
curve it would seem like we've run all
the combinatorics right and then life
emerges and then there's about a billion
years where there's just single cells
and it seems like a billion years is a
really long time to figure stuff out
they're not gonna be multi cells it's
actually when the single-cell creatures
are at a phase shift of near
self-induced extinction that leads to
the environmental pressures that lead to
multi cells and you know one narrative
of how that happened
so it's kind of the nature of universe
to do unprecedented stuff right that is
kind of what evolution means is that new
epochs are unprecedented saying we need
a miracle but we have miracles in the
post I'm saying we need an epoch shift
it is not the continuation of the
current curve that is a discrete
nonlinear phase shift and that if we
think about it as just continuation of
current curves okay these things are
getting better with tech let's just hope
they keep getting better it doesn't work
and so but if we say what are the
necessary and sufficient criteria of a
civilization that doesn't self germinate
in the presence of the emerging power we
can actually identify what those
criteria are and they're actually things
that we can do then that becomes the
only mo that makes sentences working to
bring that about but then looking at the
current political climate looking at the
current kind of the leaders that we have
at the moment do you have any hope that
they are going to be equipped to bring
this about of course not because the
they are part of the system that is
obsoleting itself do you have a sense of
how that shifts then if they can't do it
I'll say things that everyone has
probably heard when Bucky fuller
famously said don't try to fight the
existing system or fix it just build a
new one that obsoletes it that it has
the right characteristics it's very much
that when we think about the the kind of
caterpillar to butterfly metamorphosis
inside the chrysalis it's not a
caterpillar or a butterfly it's goo
right and that goo phase that liminal
phase
the caterpillar is actually dying right
because the caterpillar doesn't just
lose weight and grow wings if you look
at it the the caterpillar has a genetic
code to go gather parts right to gather
minerals and amino acids and sugars that
are going to then be reassembled into a
butterfly if the if we were just looking
at the caterpillar and we didn't know
it's gonna butterfly and we were looking
at its getting bigger and it's eating
everything it's not pollinating anything
we would predict that it eats itself
into extinction except at a certain
point it gets rich enough blood
chemistry that it triggers this movement
into the chrysalis it starts to dissolve
it gets reorganized at a you know amino
acid level into something that now
pollinates the plants that the
caterpillar decimated across these vast
spaces and helps the evolution of the
whole system
the butterfly phase could not have been
predicted from the caterpillar phase and
the so if we look at capitalism in the
military industrial complex and all
those systems as gathering parts right
very much like the caterpillar was net
consumption very much like a fetuses in
utero the fetus couldn't go past 40
weeks 50 60 it dies and the mom dies but
it also couldn't come out much earlier
because it wasn't ready to make a phase
shift it comes out when it first can it
has finally evolved to the place that it
can actually do breast milk rather than
get food from the umbilical cord
directly but it also comes out when it
has to there's a fairly narrow window of
transition the same is true for an
animal developing inside of an eggshell
or a there's a finite amount of
resources and when it runs out it has to
emerge but that's also the first time
that it can emerge that system can
handle the transition so we see in
nature this kind of precedent that these
discrete nonlinear phase shifts because
there's a curve of in utero and then
there's a shift and then there's a curve
outside but that discrete phase shift
have come through the birth canal is
different than either the phase before
after so when you're asking like or any
of the caterpillar is going to be able
to do the pollination thing it's the
wrong question right like the the
problem that we see is the caterpillars
are eating everything that's true and
and that is to gather the resources that
get assembled in a fun for a
fundamentally different set of reasons
it's if we say how do we maintain
strategic competitive
that's what the leaders are trying to do
leader of a companies trying to maintain
strategic competitive advantages grants
the other companies a country is across
other countries but of course the moment
you have some sorts of asymmetric
advantage and you deploy at everybody
sees it reverse engineers it makes
modifications on it and you just up the
level of rivalry for the entire playing
field that itself is what is terminating
the seeking of strategic competitive
advantage the the rival risk dynamics
because that is what actually self
terminates with this level of power so
it's how do we take all the
technological capacity and start to use
it for something that is not trying to
have power over but to have strength to
not be deformed by other power and be
able to be anti rivalries and etc so if
there's a society we're going from this
sort of idea of the caterpillar to the
butterfly does that mean each individual
person has to go through that same shift
and if so what does that mean well how
does that look individually yes as
families and small groups of people yes
as communities villages tribes larger
groups of people yes all the way up to
everybody so individual and collective
sense making in choice making process an
individual is necessary but it's not
sufficient if you have a bunch of people
that are making sense on their own they
can never make sense of the complexity
of the whole world if they don't figure
out how to have meaningful collaborative
dynamics to other people and if they
have collaborative dynamics with some
but then not others and they get into a
competitive dynamic than the others
figure out how to disinfect so we either
figure out anti rivalries Omni
collaborative type dynamics or we cap
out at a level of collective
intelligence less than we need so as
individuals saying okay on my own I
don't know how to change macroeconomics
I don't know how to create whatever the
post democracy governance system is I
don't know how to make a closed-loop
materials economy what can I do to it
least be starting to become a citizen of
the future world myself
one thing I'd say is stop trying to win
at the dying game and not just the dying
game but the game that's killing
everything if you're still trying to win
at that game like you can't also claim
to take seriously anything meaningful
that's one thing and then also don't
just get stuck in being angry or
hopeless or just your own personal
development and go off to a Lotus Eater
thing like actually be dedicated to
progressively better figuring out what
you can do to make a new game it works
for everybody it sounds like there's a
kind of almost spiritual dynamic to it
in terms of getting past one's own ego
if you can't get along with your family
members and your ex-partners and you're
pretty sure that you're right about
things and they're wrong about things
and you think you have any idea of how
Israel and Palestine can get along or
how the US and China can get along you
are just silly and so you really don't
get to even have a idea about politics
if you don't actually know something in
an embodied sense around how to deal
with differences and how to yeah how did
how to do real conflict resolution so it
sounds a bit Jordan Peterson clean your
room pay attention to what you can pay
attention to before you try and fix
anything else foundations or foundations
those are important so the other
critical thing is that you can't assume
that other people are going to fix these
issues and you can just kind of chill in
the world will work out that also
doesn't mean that you should freak out
and go into it existential angst on
hyperdrive without knowing what to do
but to progressively lean in more and
say okay there's a path or we can make
it but it's not a given at all that we
do yet rather than ask whether we do or
not how do I help determine that we do
how can I engage and that will require
learning a bunch of shit that you don't
currently know and that maybe nobody has
synthesized well yet and that's what
being in imaginal
in the transition from caterpillar to
butterfly really means is taking some
empowered responsibility for being
someone who's recognizing that you can't
just run the instruction manual that was
given historically and the new
instruction manual doesn't exist yet and
it's actually the time of people in that
liminal phase is to work on developing
what is what are the new structures what
does that look like for an individual to
learn like if they say if someone
watching this would say okay right I
need to learn stuff what are those
things that we need to learn well some
people might have a very clear sense of
in the picture of all that needs done
working on the future of Education and
how to facilitate the development of
young humans to be healthy sovereign
humans is really their focus and there's
certain things are going to focus on for
that or health care or the new materials
economy or whatever it is if one is
wanting to become comprehensively more
educated about civilization changes
needed writ large pay attention to the
people in this video that you resonate
with and go find more of their work and
then pay attention to the footnotes in
problem
[Music]
you